《星际迷航2：可汗之怒》
（23世纪）
Captain's Log. Stardate 8130.3.
航行日志， 星际日期8130.3
Starship Enterprise on training mission to Gamma Hydra.
企业号进行训练任务， 往GH星
Section 14, coordinates: 22/87/4.
14段， 座标为22-87-4
Approaching Neutral Zone, all systems normal and functioning.
接近中立地带， 所有系统正常
Leaving Section 14 for Section 15.
离开14段， 前往15段
Stand by. Project parabolic course to avoid entering Neutral Zone.
改行抛物线轨道， 避开中立地带
Course change projected.
轨道已改变
Captain! I'm getting something on the distress channel.
船长！ 收到求救讯号
Imperative! This is the Kobayashi Maru, 19 periods out of Altair Six.
求救！ 这是牵牛星六的马鲁号
We have struck a gravitic mine and have lost all power...
我们碰到引力地雷， 动力全失
This is the Starship Enterprise. Can you give us your coordinates?
我们是企业号， 请指示座标
Enterprise, our position is Gamma Hydra, Section 10.
我们的位置是GH第十段
In the Neutral Zone.
在中立地带
Hull penetrated, life support systems failing. Can you assist us?
船身穿洞， 维生系统失灵
Data on Kobayashi Maru.
马鲁号的资料
Third class neutronic fuel carrier, crew of 81.300 passengers.
三等中子燃料运输机乘客81300
Damn!
该死！
Mr Sulu? Plot an intercept course.
苏洛？准备进入轨道
May l remind the Captain that if a Starship enters the Zone...
恕我多言， 若星舰进入地带...
I'm aware of my responsibilities, Mister.
我知道自己的责任
Estimating two minutes to intercept.
两分钟后抵达
- Now entering the Neu tral Zone. - Warning. Neutral Zone entered.
- 进入中立地带  - 警告， 进入中立地带
We are now in violation of Treaty.
我们违反了协定
Stand by, Transporter Room, ready to beam survivors aboard.
输送室准备把生还者接上船
Captain! l've lost their signal.
船长！ 失去了他们的讯号
Sensors indicate three Klingon cruisers, bearing 316 mark 4.
感应器显示三艘克林冈舰艇驶近
- Closing fast. - Visual.
- 迅速移近   - 传送影像
Battle stations! Activate shields!
进入作战状态， 启动防护罩
- Shields activated! - Say we are on a rescue mission.
- 已经启动   - 说出我们在救人
- They're jamming all frequencies. - Klingons on attack course...
- 他们干扰频道   - 他们开始袭击
We're in over our heads. Mr Sulu! Get us out of here!
我给搞糊涂了， 快离开这里
Alert! Klingon torpedoes activated.
警报！ 克林冈人发射鱼雷
Evasive action!
马上逃走！
- Engineering! Damage report! - Main energiser hit!
- 损毁报告   - 主动力器被击中
Engage auxiliary power! Prepare to return fire!
启动辅助动力！ 准备还击！
Shields collapsing, Captain!
防护罩被毁！
- Fire all phasers! - No power to the weapons, Captain.
- 发射激光炮！   -  没有动力
Captain, it's no use! We're dead in space!
没用的  我们死定了！
Activate escape pods! Send out the Log Buoy. All hands abandon ship.
启动逃生舱和救生浮标， 弃船
All right. Open her up.
打开它
- Any suggestions, Admiral? - Prayer, Mr Saavik.
- 有何建议？   - 祈祷吧， 莎维
The Klingons don't take prisoners.
克林冈人不会俘虏人的
Lights!
开灯！
Motors on!
启动摩打
Captain?
船长？
Trainees...to the briefing room.
训练员到简报室去
Maintenance Crew, report to Bridge Simulator.
维修队到模拟控制室报到
- Physician, heal thyself. - ls that all you've got to say?
- 先治好自己   - 你只想说这些？
- What about my performance? - l'm not a drama critic.
- 我的演技如何？   - 我不是影评
Are you gonna stay with the sinking ship?
你要跟沉船共存亡吗？
- Permission to speak candidly, sir? - Granted.
- 请批准我直言   - 我批准
I don't believe this was a fair test of my command abilities.
这并不能公平测试我的指挥能力
There was no way to win.
我无法获胜
Every commander may face a no-win situation.
所有指挥官都可能会面对绝境
- Has that never occurred to you? - No, sir. lt has not.
- 你从没遇过吗？   - 没有
How we deal with death is at least as important as how we deal with life.
处理死亡跟处理生命一样重要
As l indicated, that thought had not occurred to me.
我从没想过
Well, now you have something new to think about.
现在你可以想了
Admiral? Wouldn't it be easier to put an experienced crew back on the ship?
起用有经验的队员会否较好？
Galloping around the cosmos is a game for the young, Doctor.
在宇宙飞驰是年轻人的玩意
What is that supposed to mean?
什么意思？
Aren't you dead?
你不是死了的吗？
You want to learn what efficiency rating l'll give your cadets?
想知道我给学员的效率评分吗？
I am understandably curious.
我很好奇
They destroyed the Simulator Room and you with it.
他们摧毁了模拟控制室和你
The Kobayashi Maru scenario frequently wreaks havoc
马鲁号事件经常摧毁...
with students and equipment. You took the test three times yourself.
机件和学员， 你也考了三次
Your final solution was, shall we say...unique.
最后的解决方法很独特
It had the virtue of never having been tried.
功效未经验证
Oh, by the way...thank you for this.
谢谢你
I know of your fondness for antiques.
我知道你喜爱古董
''lt was the best of times, it was the worst of times...''
这是最好的， 也是最坏的年代
- Message, Spock? - None that l'm conscious of.
- 有什么讯息？   - 没有
Except, of course, happy birthday. Surely, the best of times.
除了生日快乐， 是最好的时候
Captain Spock, Captain Spock, space shuttle leaving in 15 minutes.
冼朴队长， 太空船15分钟后出发
- Where are you off to? - The Enterprise.
- 你要去哪里？   - 企业号
I must check in before your inspection. And you?
我要在你检阅前报到， 你呢？
Home.
回家
Doctor! What beams you into this neck of the woods?
医生！ 什么风吹你来的？
''Beware of Romulans bearing gifts.''
小心带着礼物的罗武伦人
- Happy birthday, Jim! - Thanks.
- 生日快乐   - 谢谢
Romulan ale! Bones, you know this is illegal.
罗武伦酒， 你明知这是违法的
I only use it for medicinal purposes. l got aboard a ship
纯为药用， 我上了一艘船
that brings in a case now and then across the Neutral Zone.
它带来一箱， 然后走过中立地带
- Now, don't be a prig. - 2283.
- 别那样死板   - 2283年
Yeah, well, it takes this stuff a while to ferment.
这东西要一段时间发酵
Here, give me that. Now, you open this one.
给我， 你打开这个
I'm almost afraid to.
我几乎有点怕
What is it? Klingon aphrodisiacs?
是克林冈人的春药吗？
No.
不是
Bones, this is charming.
实在太好了
For most patients your age, l recommend Retinax Five.
我向像你般的病人推荐视网五号
- l'm allergic to Retinax. - Exactly. Cheers!
- 我对它会敏感的   - 对， 干杯
Cheers.
干杯
Happy birthday.
生日快乐
- l don't know what to say. - You could say thank you.
- 我不知该说什么   - 说谢谢吧
Thank you.
谢谢
Damn it, Jim! What's the matter with you?
可恶， 你怎么了？
Why are we treating your birthday like a funeral?
你的生日干嘛像葬礼一般？
- Bones, l don't want to be lectured. - What the hell do you want?
- 我不想听教训   - 你想怎么样？
This is not about age. And you know it.
你不是年龄的问题， 你知的
It's about you flying a computer when you want to be hopping galaxies!
你想翱翔天际， 却只能控制电脑
Spare me your notions of poetry. We all have our duties.
别发表伟论， 各人有自己的职责
Bull! You're hiding, hiding behind rules and regulations.
你在逃避， 躲在规章背后
- Who am l hiding from? - From yourself, Admiral!
- 我在逃避谁？   - 你自己
Don't mince words, Bones. What do you really think?
有话直说， 你在想什么？
Jim...
占
I'm your doctor and l'm your friend.
我是你的医生和朋友
Get back your command.
重返指挥岗位吧
Get it back before you turn into part of this collection.
在你变成他们的一分子之前
Before you really do grow old.
你真的变老前
Starship Log. Stardate 8130.4.
航行日志， 星际日期8130.4
Log Entry by First Officer Pavel Chekov.
大副柴可夫登录
Starship Reliant on orbital approach to Ceti Alpha Six,
星舰信心号正驶向CA6星
in connection with Project Genesis.
执行创世计划
We keep searching for a lifeless planet, to satisfy the requirements
我们不断寻找无生命的星球
of a test site for the Genesis Experiment. So far, no success.
作为实验场所， 暂时还没成功
Standard orbit, please. Mr Beach, any change in the surface scan?
标准轨道， 地面扫瞄有改变吗？
Negative. Limited atmosphere dominated by craylon gas, sand,
没有， 大气中只有克朗气体、 沙
high velocity winds. lncapable of supporting life forms.
和疾风， 无法支持生命体
Does it have to be completely lifeless?
肯定毫无生命？
You've found something?
你有发现吗？
We've picked up a minor energy flux reading on one dyno scanner.
扫瞄器接收到微弱的能量流
Damn. Are you sure? Maybe the scanner's out of adjustment.
你肯定吗？也许扫瞄器有偏差
I suppose it could be a particle of pre-animate matter,
可能是生命前期物质的分子
caught in the matrix.
埋藏在母体组织内
All right. Get on the Comm-pic to Dr Marcus.
向马博士发出通讯图像
Maybe it's something we can transplant?
我们或可利用它进行移植
You know what she'll say.
你知道她会怎样说
Now, let me get this straight. Something you can transplant?
废话少说， 你要进行移植？
Something you can transplant?
进行移植？
I don't know.
我不知道
It may only be a particle of pre-animate matter.
那可能是生命前期物质的分子
Then again, it may not. You boys have to be clear on this.
也可能不是， 你们要搞清楚
There can't be so much as a microbe, or the show's off!
即使只是细菌， 也会很麻烦
Have a look. But if it is something that can be moved...
去看一下， 但若它可带它回来...
You bet, Doctor. We're on our way.
当然， 我们去了
Don't have kittens, Genesis is going to work.
别担心， 创世是可行的
They'll remember you in one breath with Newton, Einstein, Surak!
你会跟牛津和爱因斯坦相提并论
Thanks a lot. No respect from my offspring.
谢谢， 只是儿子却不尊重我
Par for the course. Are you teaming up with me for bridge after dinner?
世界很公平的， 一起吃晚饭吧
Maybe.
也许
What is it?
你怎么了？
Every time we have dealings with Starfleet, l get nervous.
每次跟舰队接触， 我都很紧张
We are dealing with something that...
我们在做的事
...could be perverted into a dreadful weapon.
若处理不善， 会变成可怕的武器
That overgrown Boy Scout you used to know is exactly the kind of man...
你认识的空谈家正是这类人
Jim Kirk was many things, but he was never a Boy Scout!
却克绝对不是空谈家
Captain Terrell, stand by to beam down.
泰利船长， 准备传送
Chekov, are you sure these are the correct coordinates?
你肯定座标正确吗？
Captain, this is the garden spot of Ceti Alpha Six.
这是CA6最好的地方
I can barely see it.
我几乎看不到
There's nothing here! The Tricorder must be broken.
这里啥也没有， 三相器定是坏了
Chekov! Over here!
柴可夫， 这边！
Those look like cargo carriers.
看来像是货物运输机
Hey, give me a hand.
帮帮我
What the hell happened?
搞什么鬼？
If they crashed, where's the rest of the ship?
若是坠机的话， 其余残骸在哪？
What the hell is that?
那是什么？
（植物舱）
Botany Bay...
植物舱
Botany Bay?!
植物舱？
Oh, no!
糟糕！
We've got to get out of here now! Damn!
马上离开这里！ 该死！
- What about the... - Never mind that! Hurry!
- 那个...   - 别管了， 快走！
Chekov, what's the matter with you?
柴可夫， 你怎么了？
Chekov!
柴可夫！
Come on! Hurry!
快走吧！
Starship Reliant to Captain Terrell.
信心号叫泰利船长
This is Commander Kyle. Will you please respond, Captain?
我是卡莉指挥官， 请回话
Captain Terrell! Respond, please!
泰利船长！ 请回话
Let's give them a little more time.
再等一会吧
Khan!
是简！
I don't know you.
我不认识你
But you...
可是你...
I never forget a face.
我这人过目不忘
Mister...
你是...
...Chekov!
柴可夫
Isn't it?
对吧？
I'd never thought to see your face again.
我没想过会再见到你
- Chekov, who is this man? - A criminal, Captain.
- 这人是谁？   - 是罪犯
A product of late 20th century genetic engineering.
20世纪末遗传工程学的产物
- What do you want? Sir, l demand... - You are in a position
- 你想怎样？我要求...   - 你现在
to demand nothing, sir.
没权要求什么
I, on the other hand, am in a position to grant...nothing.
我亦不会给予什么
What you see is all that remains of the ship's company and crew
你看到的是植物舱硕果仅存的...
of the Botany Bay...
船员
...marooned here 15 years ago by Captain James T. Kirk.
15年前， 我们被却克船长放逐
- Listen! You men and women... - Captain! Captain...
- 你们这群男女听着...   - 船长！
Save your strength.
省口气吧
These people have sworn to live and die at my command
二百年前， 你还没出生时
200 years before you were born.
他们誓死效忠于我
Do you mean... he never told you the tale?
他从没有跟你说起吗？
To amuse your captain? No?
用来逗你的船长高兴
Never told how the Enterprise picked up the Botany Bay, lost in space,
说说企业号如何在1996年
in the year 1996, myself and the ship's company in cryogenic freeze?
把我和船员接收
- l've never even met Admiral Kirk. - Admiral?
- 我不认识却克上将   - 上将？
Admiral?!
上将？
Admiral...
上将
Never told you how... Admiral Kirk sent 70 of us into exile
没说起却克上将如何把我们...
on this barren sand heap,
放逐到这个荒漠
with only the contents of these cargo bays to sustain us?
要我们只靠货舱里的东西维生
You lie! On Ceti Alpha Five there was life!
胡说， CA5是有生命的
- A fair chance! - This is Ceti Alpha Five!
- 非常公平   - 这里就是CA5
Ceti Alpha Six exploded six months after we were left here.
我们来到这里半年， CA6就爆炸
The shock shifted the orbit of this planet and everything was laid waste!
震荡改变星球轨迹， 一切都损毁
Admiral Kirk...never bothered to check on our progress.
却克上将没察看我们的发展
It was only the fact of my genetically engineered intellect
全靠程式赋予我的智慧
that allowed us to survive.
我们才活到今天
On Earth...
在地球上
...200 years ago...
二百年前
...l was a prince...
我是王子
...with power over millions!
权倾天下
Captain Kirk was your host! You repaid his hospitality
却克船长招呼你， 你以怨报德
by trying to steal his ship and murder him!
企图偷他的船和谋杀他！
You didn't expect to find me.
你没料到会找到我
You thought this was... Ceti Alpha Six!
你以为这里是CA6
Why are you here?
你为何要来这里？
Why?!
为什么？
Allow me to introduce you to Ceti Alpha Five's only remaining
容我介绍， 这是CA5仅存的...
indigenous life form.
本土生命体
What do you think?
你觉得怎么样？
They've killed 20 of my people.
它们杀了我20个子民
Including my beloved wife.
包括我的爱妻
Oh, not all at once.
他们不是同一时间死去
And not...instantly, to be sure.
也绝非马上死去
You see, their young enter through the ears...
幼虫爬进耳朵里
...and wrap themselves around the cerebral cortex.
藏身在大脑皮层内
This has the effect of rendering the victim extremely susceptible
受到影响的受害人...
to suggestion.
会听命于人
Later, as they...grow...
然后， 幼虫长大
...follows madness.
他们会发疯
And death.
最后死亡
Khan! Listen to me!
简！ 你听我说
These are pets, of course.
它们当然是宠物
Not quite domesticated.
只是不太驯服
Khan... Captain Kirk was only doing his duty.
却克船长不过是履行职责
No!
不要！
That's better.
好一点了
Now, tell me... Why are you here?
告诉我...你们为何要来这里？
And tell me where l may find...
以及可以在哪里...
...James Kirk.
找到却克
Enterprise to Admiral Kirk's shuttle.
企业号叫却克上将的飞船
You're cleared for docking. Approach portside torpedo bay.
你可以停泊， 靠近舷边鱼雷舱
Enterprise, this is Admiral Kirk's party on final approach.
却克上将一队来到
Enterprise welcomes you. Prepare for docking.
企业号欢迎你， 准备停泊
I hate inspections.
我讨厌检阅
I'm delighted. Any chance to go aboard the Enterprise.
我很高兴有机会登上企业号
I am glad to have you at the helm for three weeks.
很高兴你能掌舵三星期
I don't think these kids can steer.
这些孩子不会掌舵
Open the airlock.
打开气塞
- Permission to come aboard, Captain. - Welcome. You know my training crew.
- 请批准上船   - 你认识训练员
They certainly know you.
他们当然认识你
Yes. We've been through death and life together.
对， 我们曾同生共死
Mr Scott, you old space dog! You're well?
史葛， 你这小子， 你好吗？
I had a wee bout, sir, but Dr McCoy pulled me through.
我有点恐惧， 但麦医生帮我克服
- A wee bout of what? - Shore leave, Admiral.
- 害怕什么？   - 上岸
- And who is this? - Midshipman First Class.
- 你是谁？   - 一等海军学生
- Peter Preston, engineer's mate! - First training voyage?
- 工程助手贝彼得   - 首次航行？
- Yes, sir! - l see.
- 是的   - 原来如此
Well...shall we start with the Engine Room?
我们从引擎室开始吧？
We'll see you there. Everything is in order.
里面见， 状况都很良好
That'll be a pleasant surprise, Mr Scott.
实在令人惊喜
I'll see you on the bridge, Admiral. Company dismissed!
待会在控制室见， 解散
他不像我预期中那样
他有什么地方让你意想不到？
他很富...人性
莎维， 没有人是完美的
Well, Mr Scott, are your cadets capable of handling a minor training cruise?
你的学员可以应付训练巡航吗？
- Give the word, Admiral! - Mr Scott, the word is given.
- 请发命令   - 可以了
Admiral, what about the rest of the inspection?
你还要检阅其他部门
Later.
稍后才继续
This is Starfleet Operations. Enterprise is cleared for departure.
这里是总部， 企业号可以起程
Admiral on the bridge.
上将在控制室
Very well, Mr Saavik. You may clear all moorings.
莎维， 可以清场
- All moorings are clear, Captain. - Thank you.
- 已经清场   - 谢谢
Lieutenant? Have you ever piloted a Starship out of spacedock?
你曾驾驶星舰离开码头吗？
Never, sir.
没有
Take her out, Mr Saavik.
出发吧， 莎维
Aye, sir.
知道
For everything there is a first time, Lieutenant. Don't you agree, Admiral?
凡事总有第一次， 对吗？
- Aft thrusters, Mr Sulu. - Aft thrusters.
- 船尾火箭推进器   - 知道
- Would you like a tranquilliser? - Ahead one quarter impulse power.
- 要吃镇定剂吗？   - 加大推动力
- We are free and clear to navigate. - Course heading, Captain?
- 我们可以航行了   - 方向是？
Captain's discretion.
由船长决定
Mr Sulu? You may...indulge yourself.
苏洛先生？由你作主吧
Aye, sir.
知道
That about do it?
仅此而已？
There can't be more information we could squeeze into the memory banks.
资料库满了
- Next time we'll design a bigger one. - Who'd build it?
- 下次设计大一点的   - 谁造的？
Dr Marcus? Comm-Pic coming in on hyperchannel.
马博士， 有人传送通讯图像
- It's the Starship Reliant. - On the screen, please, Jedda.
- 是信心号   - 播出来看看
Come in, please. This is the Reliant calling Regula One.
请回覆， 信心号叫正规一号
Repeat, this is USS Reliant.
重复， 这里是美国军舰信心号
Commander, we are receiving. This is Regula One. Go ahead.
正规一号收到， 请继续
Dr Marcus. We're en route to you and should be there in three days.
我们正朝着你方进发， 三天后到
En route? Why? We weren't expecting you for another three months.
为什么？你该在三个月后回来
- Has something happened? - Ceti Alpha Six has checked out.
- 有什么不妥   - 已经找到CA6
- Then l don't understand why you... - We have received new orders.
- 我不懂为何你...   - 收到新命令
Upon our arrival at Regula One, all materials of Project Genesis
抵达后， 关于创世计划的资料...
will be transferred to this ship for testing on Ceti Alpha Six.
都要传送到船上， 在CA6测试
Who the hell do they think they are?
他们以为自己是谁？
Commander Chekov, this is completely irregular.
指挥官， 这样做不合常规
- l have my orders. - Pin him down, Mother!
- 这是任务   - 别理他， 妈
Who gave the order?
是谁下的命令？
The order comes from... Admiral James T. Kirk.
是却克上将下的命令
I knew it! All along the military's wanted to get...
我早知道！ 军方只想抢...
This is completely improper, Commander Chekov!
这样做不合常规
I do not intend to allow Reliant or any other unauthorised personnel
我不容许任何未经授权的人...
access to our work or materials.
接触我们的资料
I'm sorry that you feel that way. The Admiral's orders are confirmed.
很抱歉， 这是上将的命令
Please prepare to deliver Genesis to us upon our arrival. Reliant out.
预备创世计划的资料， 通话完毕
Well done, Commander.
做得好
You realise, sir, they will attempt to contact Admiral Kirk
他们会尝试联络却克上将
and confirm the order.
确定指令
Hold, please.
等等
Thank you, sir.
谢谢
Lieutenant, are you wearing your hair differently?
你梳了不同的发型
It's still regulation, Admiral.
依然合符规则
May l speak, sir?
我可以说话吗？
Self-expression doesn't seem to be one of your problems.
自我表达不是你的弱项
You're bothered by your performance on the Kobayashi Maru.
你备受在马鲁号的表现困扰
- l failed to resolve the situation. - It's a test of character.
- 我解决不了   - 那是性格测试
May l ask how you dealt with the test?
我可以问你是如何处理吗？
You may ask.
你可以问
That's a little joke.
我在说笑
Humour. lt is a difficult concept.
幽默是难以理解的概念
- lt is not logical. - We learn by doing.
- 不合逻辑   - 我们从实践中学习
Who's been holding up the damn elevator?
是谁霸占着升降机？
- Did she change her hairstyle? - l hadn't noticed.
- 她改变了发型吗？   - 我没留意
Wonderful stuff, that Romulan ale.
罗武伦酒真是好酒
- Admiral Kirk? - Kirk here.
- 却克上将？   - 我是
An urgent Comm-Pic from Space Lab Regula One for you. Dr Carol Marcus.
太空实验室的马博士有急事找你
- l'll take it in my quarters, Uhura. - lt never rains but it pours.
- 我在办公室里听   - 来势汹汹
As a physician, you should appreciate the dangers of re-opening old wounds.
你该知道挖旧疮疤的危险
- Sorry. - Jim, can you read me?
- 对不起   - 你听到吗？
I can hear you, Carol. What's the matter?
我听见， 发生什么事？
Why are you taking Genesis away from us?
你为何要把创世计划抢走
Taking Genesis? Who is taking Genesis?
谁要把创世计划抢走？
- l can see you, but l can't hear. - Carol...
- 我听不到你说什么   - 嘉露
- Jim, did you give the order? - What order? Who is taking Genesis?
- 是你下令的吗？   - 什么命令？
Please help us! l won't let them have Genesis without authorisation!
帮帮我们！ 我不会随便交出来的
On whose authority can they do this?
他们凭什么这样做？
- No one's authority! - Please do something.
- 没有人这样做   - 帮帮我
- Uhura, what's happening? - Transmission jammed at source.
- 发生什么事？   - 传送受干扰
Alert Starfleet Headquarters. l want to talk to Starfleet Command.
通知总部， 我要跟指挥部联络
We must have order in here. This has to be some sort of mistake.
先别打乱阵脚， 一定有误会
Mistake?! We're all alone here.
误会？我们孤身上路
They waited until everyone was on leave to do this.
他们待大家都休假时才这么做
Reliant is supposed to be at our disposal.
信心号应该由我们支配
- Starfleet clearly never intended... - l know that, but...
- 总部肯定不会...   - 我知道...
I tried to tell you! Scientists have always been pawns of the military.
科学家总是军方的棋子
Starfleet has kept the peace for 100 years.
一百年来， 舰队都相安无事
I cannot subscribe to your interpretation of this event!
我无法赞同你对事件的诠释
You may be right, Doctor. But what about Reliant? She's on her way.
你说得对， 但信心号已经上路
Something may be wrong in Regula One. We've been told to investigate.
正规一号有麻烦， 我们要调查
If memory serves, Regula One is a scientific research laboratory.
正规一号是科研实验室
I told Starfleet Command all we had was a boatload of children.
我跟总部说过， 船上的都是孩子
But...we're the only ship in the quadrant.
但我们是这区内唯一的星舰
These cadets of yours, how will they respond under real pressure?
你的学员面对压力时反应如何？
As with all living things, each according to his gifts.
跟所有生物一样， 看天资而定
Of course, this ship is yours.
当然， 这是你的船
No, that won't be necessary. Just get me to Regula One.
不必了， 送我到正规一号就行
As a teacher on a training mission, l'm happy to command the Enterprise.
在训练时， 我乐意指挥企业号
If we are to go on actual duty, the senior officer assumes command.
但执行任务时要由高级长官指挥
It may be nothing.
也许没事的
Garbled communications. You take the ship.
只是通讯有误， 你掌舵吧
You proceed from a false assumption.
你做了错误的假设
I'm a Vulcan. l have no ego to bruise.
我是火神星人， 没有自我意识
You remind me that logic dictates your actions?
你提醒我用逻辑支配行动？
I would not remind you of that which you know so well.
我不会提起你早已清楚的事
If l may be so bold, it was a mistake for you to accept promotion.
恕我直言， 你接受升职是错误的
Commanding a Starship is your first, best destiny.
指挥星舰是你的天命和专长
Anything else is a waste of material.
其他职责都是浪费人才
I would not presume to debate you.
我不会跟你争辩
That is wise.
明智的做法
In any case...were l to invoke logic, logic clearly dictates
无论如何， 逻辑清楚显示...
that the needs of the many outweigh the needs of the few.
多数人的福祉比少数人...
Or the one.
或一个人重要
You're my superior officer. You are also my friend.
你是我的上司， 也是我的朋友
I have been and always shall be yours.
我永远是你的朋友
Stop energisers. Prepare speakers.
关掉动力器， 启动扬声器
An emergency situation has arisen. By order of Starfleet Command,
紧急情况， 根据指挥部的命令
as of now, 1800 hours, l'm assuming command of this vessel.
下午六时， 我接管星舰的指挥权
Duty officer, so note in the log. Plot a new course
职务官， 记录在案， 更改航道
for Space Laboratory Regula One. Engine Room.
到太空实验所正规一号， 引擎室
Mr Scott! We'll be going to Warp Speed.
史葛！ 使用翘速飞行
- Course plotted for Regula One. - Engage Warp engines.
- 航道已更改   - 翘速引擎已启动
- Prepare for Warp Speed. - Ready, sir.
- 准备翘速飞行   - 准备好
I know that none of you were expecting this. l'm sorry.
我知大家都没经验， 很抱歉
I'm going to have to ask you to grow up a little sooner than you expected.
我要你们快点成长
Warp Five, Sulu.
五倍翘速
So much for the little training cruise.
训练航程结速了
Course to intercept Enterprise ready, sir.
拦截企业号的航道已准备好
- Helmsman? - Sir. May l speak?
- 希曼？   - 我想说句话
We're all with you, sir.
我们都效忠于你
But consider this.
但你想想
We are free. We have a ship and the means to go where we will.
我们拥有飞船， 爱到哪里都可
We have escaped permanent exile on Ceti Alpha Five.
还摆脱了永久放逐的命运
You have proved your superior intellect...
你已证明了自己的雄才伟略
...and defeated the plans of Admiral Kirk.
挫败了却克上将的计划
You do not need to defeat him again.
实在无须再次打败他
He tasks me.
他折磨我
He tasks me, and l shall have him.
他折磨我， 我要报仇
I'll chase him round the moons of Nibia
就算要追到天涯海角
and round the Antares maelstrom and round perdition's flames
我也要找他算帐
before l give him up! Prepare to alter course.
永不放弃， 准备改变航道
Space Station Regula One, please come in.
正规一号太空站， 请回覆
Dr Marcus, please respond.
马博士， 请回答
This is Enterprise call...
这是企业号
There's no response from Regula One.
没有反应
- But no longer jammed? - No, sir. No nothing!
- 已经没有干扰？   - 没有
There are two possibilities. They're unable or unwilling to respond.
他们可能无法回覆， 或不愿回覆
- How far? - 12 hours 43 minutes, present speed.
- 距离多远？   - 12小时43分钟
Give up Genesis, she said. What does that mean? Give it up to whom?
她说要交出创世计划， 交给谁？
It might help if l knew what Genesis was, beyond the biblical reference.
若我知何谓创世计划， 或会有用
Uhura, have Dr McCoy join us in my quarters.
乌拉， 请麦医生到我的办公室
Mr Saavik? You have the con.
莎维， 你来指挥
I've got Sick Bay ready. Will someone please tell me what's going on?
病房已准备好， 发生什么事？
Computer. Request security procedure
电脑， 启动保密程序
and access to Project Genesis summary.
存取创世计划的摘要
Identify for retina scan.
视网膜扫瞄， 核对身份
Kirk...Admiral James T.
却克上将
（视网膜、 动脉和静脉吻合）
Security Scan approved.
通过保安扫瞄
Summary, please?
摘要？
（安全影带， 录影日期7130.4）
（介绍）
Project Genesis. A proposal to the Federation.
创世计划， 星盟的提案
- Carol Marcus. - Yes.
- 马嘉露   - 是的
What exactly is Genesis?
什么是创世？
Well, put simply, Genesis is life from lifelessness.
创世是从无生命中创造生命
It is a process whereby molecular structure is reorganised
把分子组织在次原子阶段重组
at the sub-atomic level into life-generating matter of equal mass.
生产相同重量的物质
Stage One of our experiments was conducted in the laboratory.
实验的首阶段在实验室进行
Stage Two will be attempted in a lifeless underground.
次阶段会在无生命的地底进行
Stage Three will involve the process on a planetary scale.
第三阶段的范围扩大至一个星球
It is our intention to introduce the Genesis device
我们意图把创世仪器
into a pre-selected area of a lifeless space body, such as a moon.
放到预先选好的无生命天体
The device is delivered, instantaneously causing
仪器装好后， 马上产生...
what we call the Genesis Effect.
创世效应
Matter is reorganised with life-generating results.
物质重组， 创造生命
Instead of a dead moon, a living, breathing planet
月球不再死寂， 变成生机勃发
capable of sustaining whatever life forms we deposit on it.
可以供养我们送到那里的生命体
Fascinating.
太好了
The moon simulated here represents a fraction of Genesis' potential,
这个模拟月球示范创世的潜力
should the Federation wish to fund the experiment to its conclusion.
若星盟愿意资助实验
When we consider the cosmic problems of population and food supply,
看看宇宙面对的人口和粮食问题
the usefulness of this process becomes clear.
就能看到这个实验的好处
This concludes our proposal. Thank you for your attention.
建议书到此为止， 谢谢
It literally is Genesis.
是名副其实的创世
The power of creation.
创造的力量
- Have they proceeded? - The tape was made a year ago.
- 开始了没？   - 录影是两年前的
I can only assume they've reached Stage Two by now.
我估计实验进行到次阶段
But, dear Lord, do you think we're intelligent enough to...
但你认为我们有没有足够的智慧
Suppose... What if this thing were used where life already exists?
若这实验在有生命的地方展开
It would destroy such life... in favour of its new matrix.
新母体就会把原有生命摧毁
Its new matrix? Do you have any idea what you're saying?
新母体？你知道自己在说什么？
I was not attempting to evaluate its moral implications.
我不会评估它的道德含意
In cosmic history it has always been easier to destroy than to create.
在历史上， 摧毁总比创造容易
Not any more! Now we can do both at the same time.
错了！ 现在两者可以同时进行
According to myth, Earth was created in six days.
据神话记载， 地球在六天内完成
Now watch out! Here comes Genesis! We'll do it for you in six minutes!
创世出现后， 六分钟就够了
Really, Dr McCoy, you must learn to govern your passions.
麦医生， 你得学会控制情绪
They will be your undoing. Logic suggests...
否则会招致失败， 逻辑说...
Logic?! My God, the man's talking about logic!
天啊！ 这人还在说逻辑
We're talking about universal Armageddon!
这是宇宙末日
- You green-blooded, inhuman... - Bridge to Admiral Kirk.
- 你这冷血的...   - 指挥部叫上将
Sensors indicate a vessel in our area, closing fast.
有一艘飞船向我方快速移近
- What do you make of her? - It's one of ours. It's Reliant.
- 对方是谁？   - 是信心号
Try the emergency channels.
尝试使用紧急频道
Picture, Mr Saavik.
传送图像
（信心号）
Slow to one-half impulse power.
把推动力减半
- Let's be friends. - Slowing to one-half impulse power.
- 当个朋友吧   - 推动力减半
Reliant in our section. This quadrant, sir. And slowing.
信心号跟我们在同区， 正在减速
Sir? May l quote General Order 12? ''On the approach of any vessel,''
规例第12条指任何飞船驶近
''when communications have not been established...''
若无法通讯的话...
The Admiral is well aware of the regulations.
上将很清楚规例
Aye, sir.
知道
Is it possible their Comm system has failed?
他们的通讯系统会不会坏了？
It would explain many things.
这会解释很多东西
They're requesting communications, sir.
他们要求通讯
Let them eat static!
别理他们！
They're still running with shields down.
他们的防护罩依然关上
Of course! We are one big happy fleet!
当然， 我们是快乐的舰队
Ah, Kirk, my old friend! Do you know the Klingon proverb that tells us
却克， 老朋友， 克林冈谚语说
revenge is a dish that is best served cold?
君子报仇， 十年未晚
It is very cold...in space.
太空是最佳的复仇场所
This is damned peculiar.
非常不妥
- Yellow Alert! - Energise defence fields!
- 黄色戒备   - 启动防卫场
A voice. They say their Chambers coil is overloading their Comm system.
对方说通讯系统负荷过重
Scanning. Their coil emissions are normal!
检查， 感应线的放射正常
- Their shields are still down. - Raise ours.
- 防护罩没升起   - 启动防护罩
- Their shields are going up! - Lock phasers on target.
- 他们升起防护罩   - 锁定目标
Locking phasers on target.
锁定目标
- They're locking phasers. - Raise shields.
- 他们瞄准我们   - 启动防护罩
Fire!
发射！
- Sulu, get those shields up! - Trying, sir.
- 马上把防护罩升起   - 我在尝试
I can't get power, sir!
没有动力
Scotty?
史葛？
- Uhura, turn off those channels! - Mr Scott on the screen.
- 把频道关上   - 史葛要通话
We're just hanging on, sir! The main energiser's out!
我们在坚持着， 主动力器毁坏了
- Try auxiliary power! - Aye, sir.
- 启动辅助动力   - 知道
Damage report.
损毁报告
- They knew exactly where to hit us. - Who knew where to hit us? And why?
- 他们清楚我们的弱点   - 是谁？
One thing is certain. We cannot escape on auxiliary power.
我们无法单凭辅助动力逃跑
Visual!
传送影像！
- Sulu, divert all power to phasers. - Too late.
- 把动力分给激光炮   - 太迟了
Hang on!
坚持着！
Scotty! What's left?
史葛！ 还剩下什么？
Just the batteries! l can have auxiliary power in a few minutes!
只有电池， 辅助动力快可启动
We don't have a few minutes!
没时间了
- Can you give me phaser power? - A few shots!
- 可以发炮吗？   - 只能发几炮
- Not enough against their shields. - Who are they?
- 未能攻破护罩   - 他们是谁？
Admiral! The commander of the Reliant is signalling!
上将！ 信心号指挥官发出信号
He wishes to discuss terms of our surrender.
他要商讨投降的条件
Visual on screen.
传送影像
Do it! While we still have time.
趁我们还有时间
On screen, sir.
已经传送了
- Khan! - You still remember, Admiral.
- 是简！   -  你还记得我
I cannot help but be touched.
教人感激不尽
I, of course, remember you!
我当然记得你
What is the meaning of this attack?! Where is the crew of the Reliant?
为何要攻击我们？船员在哪？
Surely l have made my meaning plain.
我的意图非常简单
I mean to avenge myself upon you, Admiral.
我要找你报仇雪恨
I've deprived your ship of power and will deprive you of your life!
使飞船失去动力， 还要取你性命
But l wanted you to know first who it was who had beaten you.
首先我让你知道自己败给谁
Khan...
简
If it's me you want...
你要的人是我
...l'll have myself beamed aboard. Spare my crew!
我愿意到你的船上， 放了其他人
I make you a counter-proposal. l'll agree to your terms if...
我另有提议， 我会同意这条件
...if...in addition to yourself, you hand over to me
但除了你本人
all data and material regarding the project called... Genesis.
你还得把创世的资料带给我
- Genesis? What's that? - Don't insult my intelligence.
- 创世？   - 别侮辱我的智慧
Give me some time to recall the data on our computers.
给我一点时间搜寻资料
I give you 60 seconds, Admiral.
我给你一分钟
Clear the bridge.
大家离开指挥部
At least we know he doesn't have Genesis.
至少创世计划还不在他手上
Keep nodding as though l'm still giving orders.
继续点头， 装作在听我的吩咐
Mr Saavik, punch up the data charts of Reliant's command console.
显示信心号控制室的数据图
- Hurry! - 45 seconds.
- 快点   - 45秒
The prefix code?
密码是什么？
- The chart's up, sir. - Admiral!
- 这是数据图   - 上将！
We're finding it.
找到了
- Admiral! - Please.
- 上将   - 求求你
Please, give us time. The bridge is smashed, the computers inoperative.
稍等一会， 电脑失灵了
Time is a luxury you don't have, Admiral.
时间是你得不到的奢侈品
Damn!
可恶！
- Admiral? - It's coming through now, Khan.
- 上将   - 正传送过来
Reliant's prefix number is 16309.
信心号的密码是16309
I don't understand.
我不明白
You have to learn why things work on a Starship.
你要学习星舰的处事方式
Each ship has its own combination code.
每艘船都有自己的代号
To prevent an enemy from doing what we're attempting.
为防止敌人侵占船只
Using our console to order Reliant to lower her shields.
我们在这里下令信心号卸下护罩
Assuming he hasn't changed the combination.
但愿他没改密码
Fifteen seconds.
15秒
Khan, how do we know you'll keep your word?
我怎知道你不会食言？
I've given you no word to keep, Admiral.
我没承诺过什么
In my judgment, you simply have no alternative.
只是你没有选择余地
I see your point.
我懂了
Stand by to receive our transmission.
准备接收传送吧
Mr Sulu, lock phasers on target and await my command.
将激光炮瞄准目标， 听候命令
Time's up...Admiral.
时间到了
Here it comes.
来了
Now, Mr Spock.
动手吧
Sir! Our shields are dropping!
我们的防护罩在下降
Raise them!
升起它！
I can't!
我做不到
Where's the override?!
人手操控装置在哪？
Fire!
开火！
发射！
Fire! Fire!
开火！
- We can't fire! - Why can't you?
- 不行   - 为什么？
They've damaged the photon control and the Warp Drive. We must withdraw.
他们破坏了翘速仪， 快点撤退
- No! No! - Sir, we must!
- 不！   -  一定要
The Enterprise can wait! She's not going anywhere!
企业号那里都不能去
- Sir, you did it! - l did nothing!
- 你成功了！   -  我没有
Except get caught with my breeches down. l must be getting senile.
我太掉以轻心， 我老了
Mr Saavik? You go right on quoting regulations!
莎维， 你继续引用条例
In the meantime, let's find out how badly we've been hurt.
我们去看看损毁程度
- ls the word given, Admiral? - The word is given.
- 请发命令   - 好
Warp speed.
翘速飞行
Aye.
知道
He stayed at his post... when the trainees ran!
所有学员都跑了， 他仍紧守岗位
- Admiral? This is Spock. - Yes, Spock?
- 上将， 我是冼朴   - 什么事？
Engine Room reports auxiliary power restored.
引擎室说辅助动力恢复正常
We can proceed at impulse power.
我们可以启动推动力前进
Best speed to Regula One. Kirk out.
用最快的速度驶向正规一号
I'm sorry, Scotty.
我很难过
Approaching Regula and Space Lab Regula One.
驶向太空实验室正规一号
Space Station Regula One, this is the Starship Enterprise. Come in.
正规一号， 这是企业号， 请通话
Space Station Regula One, do you read?
正规一号， 听到吗？
Space Station Regula One, this is Enterprise. Please acknowledge.
正规一号， 这是企业号， 请通话
This is Enterprise. Do you read me?
这是企业号， 听到吗？
Space Station Regula One, do you read? Please come in.
正规一号， 听到吗？请通话
There's no response, sir.
没有反应
Sensors, Captain?
感应器的情况怎样？
Still inoperative. There's no way to ascertain what's inside the station.
仍然失灵， 无法探测内部情况
No way of telling if Reliant is still in the area.
无法探测信心号的位置
What do you make of that planetoid beyond?
你对这个小行星有什么认识？
Regula is class 'D'. lt consists
正规星是丁级星
of various unremarkable ores. Essentially a great rock in space.
包括其寻常矿石， 是一块大石
- Reliant could be behind the rock. - A distinct possibility.
- 信心号可能在石后   - 很有可能
- Engineering? - Aye, sir.
- 工程室？   - 知道
Mr Scott? Do you have enough power for transporters?
动力够不够启动运输机？
Barely, sir.
仅仅足够
- l'm going down there. - Khan could be there!
- 我要进去   - 简或在里面！
He's been there, hasn't found what he wants. Who can you spare?
他未找到所需东西， 谁有空？
I can spare me.
我有空
Begging your pardon. General Order 15: "No flag officer shall beam"
规则说没有武装人员陪同下
''into a hazardous area without armed escort.''
不得擅自走进危险地区
There's no such regulation!
根本没有这条规矩！
All right, join the party. Mr Spock, the ship is yours.
一起走吧， 冼朴， 你来掌舵
Jim, be careful.
万事小心
We will!
我们会！
Indeterminate life signs.
不确定的生命迹象
Phasers on stun.
拿出激光枪
Move out.
行动
Jim!
占！
Rigor hasn't set in. This couldn't have happened too long ago.
还未僵硬， 刚死去不久
Carol...
嘉露
Enterprise calling Space Lab Regula One. Respond, please.
企业号叫正规一号， 请通话
Admiral! Over here.
上将！ 在这里
Dr Marcus, come in, please!
马博士， 请通话！
Oh, my God!
天啊！
Please acknowledge signal! Please...
请确认信号
This is Lieutenant Saavik. We're all right. Please stand by.
我是莎维副官， 一切安好
Oh, sir! lt was Khan!
长官， 是简！
- We found him on Ceti Alpha Five. - Easy...
- 我们在CA5找到他   - 冷静
He...put...creatures in our bodies!
他把生物植入我们体内
To control our minds!
控制我们的思想
It's all right. You're safe now.
没事了， 你安全了
Made us say lies...do things.
使我们说谎
But we beat him. He thought he controlled us, but he did not!
我们打败了他， 他不能控制我们
- The Captain was strong. - Captain...
- 船长很强壮   - 船长
Where's Dr Marcus? Where are the Genesis materials?
马博士和创世的资料在哪里？
He couldn't find them. Even the data banks were empty.
他找不到， 资料库也是空的
- Erased? - He tortured those people.
- 清除了？   - 他折磨那些人
But none of them would tell him anything. He went wild.
但大家都守口如瓶， 他气炸了
He slit their throats. He wanted to tear the place apart.
把他们杀死， 还想捣毁这里
But he was late. He had to get back to Reliant to blow you to bits!
但太迟了， 他要赶回信心号
Where's Reliant's crew? Dead?
信心号的船员死了吗？
Marooned on Ceti Alpha Five.
被遗弃在CA5星上
He's mad. He blames you for the death of his wife.
他疯了， 说你害死他妻子
I know what he blames me for.
我知道
The escape pods are all in place. Where's the Transporter Room?
逃生舱还在， 传送室在哪里？
- Did he make it down here? - lt was not my impression.
- 他来到这里？   - 不是的
He spent most of the time trying to wring information out of the people.
他在迫人招供时， 花了很多时间
The unit's been left on. This means nobody remained to turn it off.
机器还开着， 所有人都死了
Those people bought escape time for Genesis with their lives.
他们以生命换取运走资料的时间
This is not logical. These coordinates are deep inside Regula.
没道理， 这些座标在正规星深处
A planetoid we know to be lifeless.
这小星球没有生命
If Stage Two was completed, it was going to be underground.
若次阶段已完成， 该在地下
- Underground, she said! - Stage Two of what?
- 是地下   - 什么次阶段？
- Kirk to Enterprise. - Spock here.
- 却克叫企业号   - 我是冼朴
Captain Spock, damage report.
损毁报告
If we go by the book, like Saavik, hours could seem like days.
若依书直说， 你会觉得度日如年
- Let's have it, Captain. - The situation is grave.
- 有话直说   - 情况很严峻
We won't have main power for six days.
主动力在六天后才能恢复
Auxiliary power has temporarily failed.
辅助动力暂时失灵
Restoration may be possible in two days...by the book, Admiral.
按常规， 要两天后才能修理
You can't even beam us back?
无法把我们送回船上？
Not at present.
暂时不能
Captain Spock. If you don't hear from us within one hour,
若一小时内没有我们的消息
your orders are to restore what power you can,
就尽量修复动力系统
take the Enterprise to the nearest Starbase
把企业号驶到最近的基地
and alert Starfleet Command when out of jamming range.
离开干扰范围后， 马上通知总部
Sir, we won't leave you behind!
我们不能丢下你不管
Uhura, if you don't hear from us, there won't be anybody behind.
若失去联络， 就表示无人生还
Gentlemen, you can stay here, or...
你们可以留下来...
If it's all the same, Admiral, we'd like to share the risk.
我们愿意共同承担危险
Right. Let's go. Saavik.
好， 走吧， 莎维
- Go? Where are we going? - Where they went.
- 走到哪里去？   - 他们去的地方
Suppose they went nowhere?
若他们哪儿都没去呢？
Then this will be your big chance to get away from it all.
那这是逃走的好机会
Admiral...
上将
Genesis, l presume.
是创世吧
Phasers down!
放下武器！
You!
你！
- Where's Dr Marcus? - l'm Dr Marcus!
- 马博士在哪？   - 我就是了
Jim!
占
Is that David?
他是大卫吗？
Mother! He killed everybody we left behind.
妈！ 他把余下的人杀光了
Of course he didn't. David, you're just making this harder.
他不会的， 别把事情越弄越复杂
I'm afraid it's even harder than you think, Doctor.
比你想像中更复杂
Please don't move.
别动
Chekov!
柴可夫！
I'm...sorry, Admiral.
对不起
Your Excellency, have you been listening?
大人， 你听到吗？
I have indeed, Captain. You have done well.
听到了， 你做得很好
I knew it! You son of a bitch!
我早知道， 混蛋！
- Don't move! Anybody! - Captain? We are waiting.
- 别动   - 船长， 我们在等着
- What's the delay? - All is well, sir.
- 为何要延误？   - 没事
You have the coordinates to beam up Genesis.
你有传送创世的座标
First things first, Captain.
先办妥最重要的事
Kill Admiral Kirk.
把却克上将干掉
Sir, that is difficult. l...
我难以下手， 我...
- I try to obey, but... - Kill him!
- 我想遵从的， 但...   - 杀了他！
I...
我...
Kill him, Terrell, now!
马上杀了他
God's sakes!
天啊！
What is it?
这是什么？
Khan, you bloodsucker!
简！ 你这卑鄙小人！
You're gonna have to do your own dirty work now! Do you hear me?
有种就放马过来！
Kirk!
却克！
Kirk, you're still alive, my old friend.
老朋友， 你还未死
Still, ''old friend''! You've managed to kill just about everyone else,
对， 老朋友！ 你几乎干掉所有人
but like a poor marksman, you keep missing the target.
但却打不中目标
Perhaps l no longer need to try, Admiral.
我不用再尝试
He can't take it!
不能让他抢走
Khan!
简！
You've got Genesis, but you don't have me!
你得到创世， 却杀不了我
You were going to kill me, Khan! You're going to have to come here!
你要杀我， 就要过来
I've done far worse than kill you.
我要你比死更难受
I've hurt you.
我伤害了你
And l wish to go on...hurting you.
我要继续伤害你
I shall leave you as you left me.
把你丢下， 像你丢下我一样
As you left her.
像你丢下她一样
Marooned for all eternity, in the centre of a dead planet.
永远被遗弃在死寂的星球上
Buried alive!
生葬！
Khan!
简！
This is Lieutenant Saavik calling Enterprise. Can you read us?
莎维叫企业号， 听到吗？
- He's coming around. - Pavel?
- 他醒来了   - 柴可夫？
It's no use, Admiral. They're still jamming all channels.
没用的， 他们干扰了所有频道
If Enterprise followed orders, she's gone.
企业号遵从命令走了
If she couldn't obey, she's finished.
若她跑不掉就死定了
So are we, it looks like.
跟我们一样
I don't understand! Who's responsible for all this?
我不明白！ 到底是什么一回事？
Who is Khan?
简是谁？
- It's a long story. - We appear to have plenty of time.
- 说来话长   - 我们有的是时间
Is there anything to eat? l don't know about you, but l'm starved.
有食物吗？我饿坏了
How can you think of food now?
你怎么会想到食物的？
First order of business. Survival.
最重要的是活下去
There is food in the Genesis cave.
创世洞穴内有食物
Enough to last a lifetime... if necessary.
有需要的话， 足够维持一辈子
We thought this was Genesis.
还以为这里是创世
It took the Starfleet Corps of Engineers
总部的工程师
ten months in spacesuits to tunnel out all this.
花了十个月才把这里挖好
What we did in there, we did in a day.
这里的工作却一天内完成
David, why don't you show Dr McCoy and the Lieutenant our idea of food?
让麦医生和副官看看我们的食物
- We can't just sit here! - Oh, yes, we can.
- 我们不能光坐着   - 可以的
This is just to give us something to do, isn't it?
总算是有事可做吧
Come on.
来吧
- Admiral? - As your teacher, Mr Spock, says,
- 上将？   - 你的老师冼朴说
''l like to think that there always are...possibilities.''
凡事总有机会
I did what you wanted.
我如你所愿
I stayed away.
我走了
Why didn't you tell me?
何不早跟我说？
How can you ask me that?
你怎能这么说？
Were we together?
我们不是一起的吗？
Were we going to be?
不是说好会一起的吗？
You had your world and l had mine.
我们各自拥有一片天
And l wanted him in mine.
我希望他留在我身旁
Not chasing through the universe with his father!
而不是跟爸爸在宇宙间奔波
Actually...he's a lot like you.
他很像你
In many ways.
很多方面都像
Please tell me what you're feeling.
你有什么感觉
There's a man out there l haven't seen in 15 years,
那个男人
who's trying to kill me.
他想杀我
You show me a son that'd be happy to help him.
我的儿子却乐于帮助他
My son...
儿子...
My life that could have been...
我的人生本可很丰盛
...and wasn't.
事实却不然
And what am l feeling?
我的感觉？
Old.
衰老
Worn out.
疲惫
Let me show you something...
我给你看一些东西
...that'll make you feel young, as when the world was new.
能使你返老还童
Impulse power restored.
推动力已修复
Excellent. More than a match for poor Enterprise.
好， 领先可怜的企业号
You did all this in a day?
你在一天内完成？
The matrix formed in a day.
母体在一天内形成
The life forms grew later, at a substantially accelerated rate.
生命体极快速地成长
Jim! This is fantastic! Have you ever seen the like?
很厉害， 你见过这样的情景吗？
Can l cook or can't l?
我很厉害吧？
Where is she?
她在哪里？
Sir? May l ask you a question?
我可以发问吗？
- What's on your mind, Lieutenant? - The Kobayashi Maru.
- 你在想什么？   - 马鲁号
Are you asking if this is that scenario?
你想问现在像那情况吗？
On the test, will you tell me what you did? l would really like to know.
我很想知道你如何应付那测试
Lieutenant, you are looking at the only Starfleet cadet
在所有星舰学员中
who ever beat the no-win scenario.
唯有他能在绝境中求胜
How?
怎样做？
I reprogrammed the simulation so it was possible to rescue the ship.
我把电脑程序改编， 拯救船只
- What? - He cheated!
- 什么？   - 他作弊！
I changed the conditions of the test.
我更改测试条件
I got a commendation for original thinking. l don't like to lose.
他们赞扬我的想法， 我不爱输
Then you never faced that situation...faced death?
你不曾面对死亡？
I don't believe in a no-win scenario.
我不相信有绝境
- Spock. It's two hours. Ready? - Right on schedule.
- 两小时了， 准备好吗？   - 行了
Just give us your coordinates and we'll beam you aboard.
请说出座标， 我们把你们送上来
I don't like to lose.
我不爱输
But we were immobilised. Captain Spock said it'd be two days.
但我们无法动弹， 要两天才修复
Lieutenant, you of all people go by the book. Spock!
从常规想想吧， 冼朴
- You know Dr Marcus. - Of course.
- 你认识马博士   - 当然
- l'm taking this bunch to Sick Bay. - By the book?
- 我把他带到病房   - 常规？
Regulation 46A. ''If transmissions are monitored during battle...''
46A， 若战时传送遭监听的话
''...no uncoded messages on an open channel''.
公开频道的讯息必须加密码
- You lied. - l exaggerated.
- 你撒谎   - 夸张而已
Hours instead of days. Now we have minutes instead of hours.
天代表小时， 分钟代表小时
- lnoperative below C-Deck. - What is working?
- 丙甲板失灵   - 有什么还能动？
We have partial main power. Best we could do in two hours.
部分主动力失灵， 两小时内修好
- Admiral on the bridge. - Battle stations!
- 上将在控制室   - 作战状态
Tactical!
作战策略
She can still outrun us... and outgun us.
她的速度较快， 火力较大
- But there is the Mutara Nebula. - Scotty, can we make it inside?
- 那是缪他星云   - 可以进去吗？
The energiser's bypassed, so don't give me too many bumps.
动力器还未修复， 别再被击中
- No promises. On your way. - Trouble with the nebula
- 不能保证   - 星云的问题是...
is all that static discharge and gas clouds our tactical display.
静电和烟云会干扰显示器
Visual won't function and shields will be useless.
我们看不到东西， 也不能用护罩
Sauce for the goose, Mr Saavik.
害己亦害人
The odds will be even.
大家势均力敌
There she is!
她在那里！
Not so wounded as we were led to believe.
损毁程度没我们想像中严重
So much the better.
好极了
Estimating nebula penetration in 2.2 minutes.
2.2分钟后进入星云
Reliant is closing.
信心号正迫近
If they go in there, we'll lose them.
他们进去后就无法追踪
Explain it to them.
教训他们
- That was close. - They don't want us going in there.
- 好险   - 他们不想我们进去
One minute to nebula perimeter.
一分钟后进入星云
Why are we slowing?
干嘛要减速？
We daren't follow them into the nebula. Our shields would be useless.
若进入星云， 保护罩就会失效
- They are reducing speed. - Uhura, patch me in.
- 他们在减速   - 给我连络他
You're on, Admiral.
可以了
Admiral Kirk here. We tried it your way, Khan. Game for a rematch?
我是却克上将， 有兴趣重赛吗？
Khan! l'm laughing
我在嘲笑你的...
at the ''superior intellect''.
“超人智慧”
- Full impulse power. - No, sir!
- 全速前进   - 不可以
You have Genesis. You can have whatever...
你得到创世， 已是万能了
Full power! Damn you!
全速前进！ 可恶！
I'll say this for him, he's consistent.
他的性格始终如一
We are now entering the Mutara Nebula.
我们正进入缪他星云
Emergency lights.
紧急灯光
Tactical.
战术
Inoperative.
失灵
Raise the shields.
升起防护罩
As l feared, sir, not functional. l'm reducing speed.
果然不行， 我在减速
Target, sir.
目标
- Phaser lock inoperative. - Best guess, Sulu. Fire when ready.
- 无法锁定目标   - 测量好就开火
Aft torpedoes! Fire!
船尾鱼雷， 开火！
Hold your course.
稳定航道
Evasive starboard!
右舷！
Fire!
开火！
Damage, Mr Scott?
损毁报告
Admiral, l've got to take the mains off the line.
我要把主要部分关掉
- The radiation... - Scotty?!
- 幅射...   - 史葛？
Joachim!
尤金
Yours...is the...superior...
你是最...伟大的
I shall avenge you!
我会替你报仇
Could you use another hand, Admiral?
可以另觅人选吗？
Man the weapons console, Mr Chekov.
柴可夫， 控制武器室
- Spock. - Sporadic energy readings.
- 冼朴   - 能源读数
Port side, aft. Could be an impulse turn.
船尾左舷， 可能是转向
He won't break off now.
他不肯罢手
He followed me this far, he'll be back.
他跟纵了我那么久， 定会回来
But from where?
从哪里回来？
He's intelligent, but not experienced.
他很聪明， 但缺乏经验
His pattern indicates two-dimensional thinking.
他使用二元思维模式
- Full stop. - Full stop, sir.
- 停止   - 停止
Z-minus 10,000 metres. Stand by photon torpedoes.
负一万米， 光子鱼雷候命
Torpedoes ready, sir.
鱼雷准备好了
Look sharp.
注意
Fire!
开火！
Uhura, send to Commander, Reliant Prepare to be boarded
给信心号指挥官发讯， 准备上船
Aye, sir.
知道
Commander, Reliant, this is Enterprise.
信心号指挥官， 这里是企业号
Surrender and prepare to be boarded.
快投降， 准备上船
Enterprise to Reliant. You are ordered to surrender your vessel.
企业号叫信心号， 投降和弃船
Reliant! Come in, Reliant. You are ordered to surrender your vessel.
信心号， 我们命令你投降
Enterprise to Reliant. You're ordered to surrender your vessel. Respond.
No, Kirk.
不， 却克
The game's not over.
游戏还没完结
To the last... l will grapple with thee!
我会跟你拼到底！
Admiral? Scanning an energy source on Reliant.
探测到信心号有股能量
A pattern l've never seen before.
我从没见过这模式
- It's the Genesis Wave! - What?
- 是创世的电波   - 什么？
They're on a build-up to detonation!
他们要引爆
- How soon? - We encoded four minutes.
- 多久后？   -  四分钟
- We'll beam aboard and stop it. - You can't.
- 我们要上船阻止他   - 不行
Scotty! l need Warp Speed in three minutes, or we're all dead.
三分钟后预备翘速飞行
- No response, Admiral. - Scotty!
- 没反应   - 史葛
Mr Sulu, get us out of here. Best possible speed.
苏洛， 尽快带我们离开这里
Are you out of your Vulcan mind?! No human can tolerate that radiation!
你疯了吗？人类无法忍受那幅射
As you are so fond of observing, Doctor, l am not human.
你真是观察入微， 我不是人类
- You're not going in there! - Perhaps you're right.
- 你不能进去   - 你说得对
- What is Mr Scott's condition? - Well, l don't think that he...
- 史葛怎样了？   - 我想他...
I'm sorry, Doctor, l have no time to discuss this logically.
对不起， 我没时间合理地解释
Remember.
记着
（辐射）
Spock! Get out of there! Spock!
冼朴！ 快离开
Spock! Get out of there!
冼朴！ 出来！
- Time from my mark? - Two minutes ten seconds.
- 时间？   - 两分钟零十秒
Engine Room! What's happening?
引擎室！ 发生什么事？
- Spock! - Good God! Get out of there!
- 冼朴   - 你快出来
No! God, don't!
天啊， 不要！
Time?
时间？
Three minutes, 30 seconds.
3分30秒
- Distance from Reliant? - 4,000 kilometres.
- 与信心号的距离？   -  四千公里
We're not going to make it, are we?
我们逃不了吧？
No!
不！
No! You can't get away!
你跑不了的
From hell's heart, l stab at thee!
我从地狱把你干掉
For hate's sake, l spit my last breath...at thee!
我用最后一口气唾骂你
- Sir! The mains are back on line! - Bless you, Scotty. Go, Sulu!
- 主电流回复了   - 好极， 走吧
My God, Carol. Look at it.
嘉露， 你看
Engine Room? Well done, Scotty.
引擎室？做得好， 史葛
Jim! l think you'd better get down here.
占， 你马上下来
- Bones? - Better hurry.
- 什么事？   - 快点
Saavik, take the con.
莎维， 你来控制
No! You'll flood the whole compartment!
不， 船舱会充满幅射！
- He'll die! - Sir! He's dead already.
- 他会死的   - 他已死了
It's too late, Jim.
太迟了
Spock!
冼朴！
Ship...out of danger?
飞船脱险了吧？
Yes.
是的
Don't grieve, Admiral.
别难过
It is logical.
这很合符逻辑
The needs of the many...outweigh...
多数人的福祉...
...the needs of the few.
比少数人...
Or the one.
或一个人的要紧
I never took... the Kobayashi Maru test.
我没接受马鲁号测验
Until now.
直到现在
What do you think of my solution?
我的解决方法怎样？
Spock!
冼朴！
I have been...
我一直...
...and always shall be...
永远都是...
...your friend.
你的朋友
Live long...and prosper!
长命百岁， 活得丰盛
No!
不要！
We are assembled here today to pay final respects to our honoured dead.
我们齐集在此， 作最后致敬
And yet it should be noted that, in the midst of our sorrow,
尽管如此哀伤， 我们要记着
this death takes place in the shadow of new life.
死亡过后， 必有新生
The sunrise of a new world.
新世界定会出现
A world that our beloved comrade gave his life to protect and nourish.
我们的同伴以生命去保护它
He did not feel his sacrifice a vain or empty one.
他没有白白牺牲
And we will not debate his profound wisdom at these proceedings.
我们不会质疑他的举动和智慧
Of my friend, l can only say this...
我只能说， 在我的朋友中
Of all the souls l have encountered in my travels...
在我航行以来认识的人中...
...his was the most...
他最富...
...human.
人情味
Honours...hup!
立正
Come.
进来吧
I don't mean to intrude.
我无意打扰你
No, not at all. l should be on the bridge.
没有， 我要到控制室去
- Can l talk to you for a minute? - Would you like a drink?
- 我想跟你谈谈   - 要喝点什么？
Lieutenant Saavik was right.
莎维说得对
You never have faced a death.
你从没面对死亡
No, not like this.
不是这样的
I haven't faced death.
我从没面对死亡
I've cheated death.
我使诈
I've tricked my way out of death...
运用谋略远离死亡
...and patted myself on the back for my ingenuity.
把自己藏在计谋之后
- l know nothing. - You knew enough to tell Saavik
- 我什么也不懂   - 你跟莎维说
that how we face death is at least as important as how we face life.
处理死亡跟处理生命一样重要
- Just words. - But good words.
- 我说说而已   - 但说得好
That's where ideas begin. Maybe you should listen to them.
这番话能带出真理， 你该听从
I was wrong about you. And l'm sorry.
我看错了你， 对不起
Is that what you came here to say?
你要说的就这么多？
Mainly.
大概是
And also that l'm...proud...
还有， 我很自豪
...very proud...to be your son.
能成为你的儿子
Captain's Log, Stardate 8141.6. Starship Enterprise departing
航行日志， 星际日期8141.6
for Ceti Alpha Five to pick up the crew of USS Reliant.
企业号到CA5接应信心号船员
All is well.
大家都没事
And yet, l can't help wondering about the friend l leave behind.
我不断想起我遗下的朋友
''There are always possibilities, '' Spock said.
冼朴说， 凡事总有机会
And if Genesis is indeed ''life from death'',
若创世从死亡中创出生命
I must return to this place again.
那我一定要再来这里
He's really not dead. As long as we remember him.
他没死， 他活在我们的记忆中
''It's a far, far better thing l do than l have ever done before.''
这是我所做过最好的事
''A far better resting place...''
一个以我所知道...
''that l go to than l've ever known.''
最好的安息之所
Is that a poem?
那是诗吗？
Something Spock was trying to tell me. On my birthday.
是冼朴想在我生日上说的话
You OK, Jim? How do you feel?
你没事吧， 你觉得怎样？
Young.
年轻
I feel young.
感觉很年轻
Space, the final frontier.
太空， 最后的无人地带
These are the continuing voyages of the Starship Enterprise.
星舰企业号继续旅程
Her ongoing mission... to explore strange new worlds.
她的任务是要开发新世界
To seek out new life forms and new civilisations.
寻找新的生命与文明
To boldly go... where no man has gone before.
勇敢地朝无人曾踏足之地进发